Indiana University Graduate Library School Dean's records, 1961-1992 C167
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Graduate Library School Dean's records
1961-1992
1969-1980
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University, Bloomington. Graduate Library School
C167
7.4 cubic feet 8 boxes
Bernard M. Fry served as the Dean of Indiana University's Graduate Library School from 1967 to 1980 and upon his retirement in 1984 he became Professor Emeritus of Library Science. Under Fry's leadership, the Research Center for Library and Information Science was established, and the Graduate Library School was recognized both nationally and internationally as a top five school in the field. The collection is comprised of materials relating to Fry's activities as Dean of the Graduate Library School. The majority of the collection consists of administrative and proposed research study files related to the Research Center for Library and Information Science.
Access Restrictions
Select files closed to researchers. These are indicated in the folder list.
Advance notice required for access to collection.
Administrative History
During the 1930 summer session, Indiana University offered its first class for the preparation of school librarians. The class was taught through the School of Education and was offered only in the summer until 1938, when the class was expanded and offered throughout the entire school year. That same year, Margaret I. Rufsvold came to I.U. to help develop the Library Science curriculum.
In 1947, the Division of Library Science (DLS) was established within the School of Education, with Rufsvold as its director. DLS offered an undergraduate program consisting of eighteen semester hours of work and ten graduate semester hours that were only offered in the summer. At the time, the Division concentrated on training individuals for work in school and public libraries. Students focusing on school librarianship were granted a school librarian's provisional certificate in the library science area. The certificate was valid for five years and could be converted to a first-grade certificate if a Master's degree was acquired. In 1949, the curriculum was expanded to include a five year program that would lead to a Master of Arts with a major in Library Science.
In 1951, DLS moved to the new Education Building. The program grew further to include two new degrees. The first was a Master of Arts degree with a major in Library Science for persons interested in becoming school librarians. The second was offered jointly through the College of Arts and Sciences and the School of Medicine, and was a Bachelor of Science degree in Medical Record Librarianship. That same year the American Library Association (ALA) adopted new standards for accreditation of library schools. In April 1953, after two years of preparation, the DLS was granted accreditation by the ALA.
In the early 1960's discussion of a new library building was introduced as the DLS program continued to expand, and by the end of 1964 the Program began to offer courses at the I.U. regional campuses. That same year discussions began to establish a doctoral program in library science, which eventually led to the creation of a Graduate Library School in 1966 and a split between Library Science and the School of Education. The result was The School of Library and Information Science (SLIS).
Rufsvold held the title of Dean for the newly created school for two months before relinquishing her administrative duties in order to teach full time. Charles H. McMullen served as acting dean from August 1966 through June 1967, when Bernard Fry was named to the post, a position he held until his retirement in 1980.
During Fry's tenure, the school was noted nationally and internationally as being in the top five schools in the field. Fry also initiated The Research Center for Library and Information Science, which produced major studies for the National Science Foundation, the Department of Defense, and the Department of Education. He retired from the IU faculty in 1984 and was awarded the title Professor Emeritus of Library Science.
In July of 2013, SLIS merged with the School of Informatics and Computing and became the Department of Information and Library Science.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into five series: Administration, Committees, Conferences and panels, Correspondence, and Research and study proposals. The Administration series is further arranged to include a General and Long Range Planning subseries. The Conferences and Panels series contains subseries of General and ERIC Materials [Education Resource Information Center]. The Research and Study Proposals series is further arranged into three subseries of General, National Science Foundation, and Student Dissertation and Research Proposals.
Scope and Content Note
The Dean's Office Graduate Library School records span the years 1961-1992 and consist largely of the files of Bernard M. Fry, who was Dean from 1967-1980. There are five series in the collection including Administrative records, Committee files, Conferences and Panels, Correspondence, and Research and Study Proposals.
The Administrative records (1961-1986) consists of files related to Fry's responsibilities as Dean of the Library School and is divided into two sub-series. The General sub-series (1961-1986) includes information concerning accreditation, budget planning, and general administrative activities relating to the functions of the Library School. The Long Range Planning subseries (1969-1980) contains material related to the long range planning process for the School.
The Committees series (1965-1985) contains materials related to committees on which Fry served in his capacity as Dean of the Library School, such as the Accreditation Committee, the Committee on Institutional Cooperation, and the Continuing Education Committee.
The third series, Conferences and panels (1970-1981), contains materials related to conferences and panels which Fry either attended or served on in his capacity as Dean of the Library School and is divided into two separate sub-series. The General sub-series (1970-1981) contains information relating to assorted conferences, including the American Library Association Council Annual Conference, and the Copyright Conference. The ERIC Materials (1970-1973) subseries, contains information specifically concerning panels run by the Education and Resource Information Center (ERIC).
The fourth series, Correspondence (1972-1992), consists of correspondence relating to Fry's role as Dean of the Library School. Noteworthy correspondents include Herb White and Martin M. Cummings. It should be noted that related correspondence to Fry's tenure as dean can also be found in his personal papers (C166).
The last series, Research and study proposals (1966-1982), contains materials about various research and study proposals and information related to projects involving the Department of Education and Library School and is further divided into three series. The General subseries (1966-1982) includes survey questionnaires for journal publications and research proposals, as well as material relating to research and articles written under the direction of the Graduate Library School. The subseries ERIC Research (1969-1977) consists of research conducted by Library Graduate School faculty, and the National Science Foundation records (1972-1978) consists of research materials related to studies conducted by the Research Center for Library and Information Science for the NSF. The subseries Student Dissertation and Research Proposals (1972-1978) consists of dissertations and proposals submitted to Dean Fry by IU students.
Related Material
For university records: Additional records such as newsletters, annual reports, bulletins, and publications may be accessed in the Archives of Institutional Memory
Archived web sites for this Department may be included in Archive-It
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database
Acquisition Information
1997/001
Provenance
Transferred from June Fry to the University Archives, October 21, 1998.
Library schools --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Library schools --Indiana --Bloomington --History --20th century --Sources.; Library schools --Indiana --Bloomington --Records and correspondence.; Fry, Bernard M. (Bernard Mitchell), 1915-1994; Indiana University, Bloomington. Graduate Library School -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. Graduate Library School -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University, Bloomington. Graduate Library School -- Administration -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Indiana University. Graduate Library School -- Archives; Indiana University. Graduate Library School -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. Graduate Library School -- Administration -- History -- 20th century -- Sources
- Administrative files, 1961-1986; undated (Box 1)
  - General, 1961-1986; undated (Box 1)
    - Action, 1976 (Box 1)
    - American Library Association (Box 1)
      - General, 1972-1981 (Box 1)
      - Accreditation (Box 1)
        - 1975/1976 (Box 1)
        - 1976 (Box 1)
    - Anniversary Seminar, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Application for an Institute for Trainee in Librarianship, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Applicants for School Librarianship, Search and Screen, 1981 (Box 1)
      Conditions Governing Access
      (Restricted)
    - Budget (Box 1)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
      - Planning Conference, 1974-75 (Box 1)
    - Burchinal Reports, 1968-72 (Box 1)
    - Campus Report, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Carter, Vice President, and American Library Association, 1970-1976 (Box 1)
    - Class Syllabi and Papers (Written by Others), 1961 (Box 1)
    - Cole, Fred C. Council on Library Resources, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
    - Coleman, Earl Plenum Publishing Company, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Continuing Library Education Network and Exchange (CLENE), 1979 (Box 1)
    - Control Data Corporation, 1968 (Box 1)
    - Course Offerings, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Dean of Faculties Memoes GLS, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Department of Education Budget, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Economics of Library Publishing Background, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
    - Equipment File, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Computer Literacy Program, 1983-84 (Box 1)
    - Government Documents, 1965-1974 (Box 1)
    - Government Publications, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Library School and Branch Libraries, Application Forms and Search Material, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Library School (Box 1)
      - Altman, Ellen, 1971-1983 (Box 1)
      - Budget, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
      - Budget, Status, Correspondence, 1973-77 (Box 1)
      - Faculty, Reed, Sarah (Search and Screen), 1971/-1975 (Box 1)
      - Press Clippings, 1970-1974 (Box 1)
      - Research Center, 1977 (Box 1)
      - Screen Committee Advertisements, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
      - Curriculum, 1978-1979 (Box 1)
    - Indiana State Library, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
    - Indiana University, American Library Association Accreditation, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Indiana University, Commencement, 1986 (Box 1)
    - Info Overload and Knowledge Base Programs, undated (Box 1)
    - Info Science, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Information Science Development, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Institute for Training in Librarianship, 1970 (Box 1)
    - IU Directory of Faculty with International Interests, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Late Applications (Search & Screen), 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - Letters of Interest for Teaching in Graduate Library School, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Library of Congress (LC) Internship Nomination Votes, 1973-75 (Box 1)
    - LSCA Proposal to Microfilm Indiana Card Catalog, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Midwest Universities Consortium for International Activities, Inc. (MUCIA) - Haile Sellassie University//AID-type Proposal, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Minority Student Graduates (Classification), 1979, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Graduate Library School), undated; (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - National Library of Medicine (NLM) Request for Proposal (RFP) to catalog backlog (Weintraub interested), 1974 (Box 1)
    - Negro Programs, 1968-1971 (Box 1)
    - Ohrn, Steven, African Studies Indiana University, undated (Box 1)
    - Pending File, Library and Information Science Today Projects, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Placement Interviews, American Library Association, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Private Sector, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Proceedings (funding requests for), 1977 (Box 1)
    - Program of In-Service Training for Egyptian Information, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Progress Reports: Reading, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Reappointment Recommendations Due During, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - School of Library Information Studies Correspondence and Other Documents, 1983 (Box 2)
    - School of Library and Information Science (SLIS) Ph.D. Program, 1982-1985 (Box 2)
    - A Self Study Report for the Committee on Accreditation of the American Library Association (Box 2)
      - Graduate Library School, November 1975 (Box 2)
    - Search and Screen (Box 2)
      - Applicants (part-time) Not Currently Considered, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Applicants Tentatively Rejected, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Dean's Position for Graduate Library School, 1980 (Box 2)
      - Procedural Replacement for Dr. Eva Kiewitt, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Statistics on Library Schools, 1975-1978 (Box 2)
    - Summer Sessions, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Summer Teaching Faculty (Guest Professors), 1978-79 (Box 2)
    - Title IIB Institute News Releases, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Training of Foreign Scientists and Technologists in Applications of Technology, 1972/1974 (Box 2)
    - URBANDOC, undated (Box 2)
    - Use Studies, Use Needs, 1976 (Box 2)
    - Wright, Marie T., 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Long Range Planning, 1969-1980 (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2)
      - 1974 (Box 2)
      - 1978 (Box 2)
    - Herb White article Library Effectiveness, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Project Notebook, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
    - Technical Information (Box 2)
      - Support Activities (TISA) (Box 2)
        - 1 of 4, 1971 (Box 2)
        - 2 of 4, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
        - 3 of 4, 1969-1973 (Box 2)
        - 4 of 4, 1969 (Box 2)
        - Conference, San Antonio, 1972; (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - Phase II (Box 2)
        - General, 1973 (Box 2)
        - Final Report, 1973 (Box 2)
- Committees, 1965-1985 (Box 2)
  - Advisory Committee (Box 2)
    - Letter re: Instrument Drafts, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Meeting, 1974 (Box 2)
  - American Library Association (Box 3)
    - Accreditation Committee (Box 3)
      - 1972-1984 (Box 3)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 3)
    - Council, 1979-1982 (Box 3)
    - Los Angeles - Government Publications Review, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Meeting, July 8-9, 1985 (Box 3)
    - State Documents Round Table, Program Planning, 1973 (Box 3)
  - American National Standards Committee, 1973-74 (Box 3)
  - Committee on Accreditation (COA), 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (CIC), 1977-1978 (Box 3)
  - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (CIC) Meeting, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Continuing Education Committee, 1978 (Box 3)
  - Curriculum Committee (Box 3)
    - 1965-1969 (Box 3)
    - #1 and 1a 504, 508, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Meeting, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Background and Unfinished Division, 1967 (Box 3)
    - General, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Preliminary Meeting, January 7, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Sub Committee, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Goals and Objectives Committee (Box 3)
    - American Library Association Accreditation, 1982 (Box 3)
    - SLIS, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Graduate Library School General Advisory Committee, 1970-1975 (Box 3)
  - Indiana Committee for the Humanities (NEH), 1974 (Box 3)
  - Second Advisory Committee Meeting, 1975 (Box 3)
- Conferences and Panels, 1970-1981; undated (Box 3)
  - General, 1970-1981 (Box 3)
    - American Library Association Council Annual Conference, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Copyright Conference (Box 3)
      - General (Box 3)
        - 1975-1977 (Box 3)
        - 1975-1976 (Box 3)
        - 1976 (Box 3)
        - 1977 (Box 3)
      - Conference Correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 3)
    - Deans' Meeting (New York), March 1980 (Box 4)
    - ILA Round Table, Continuing Library Education Network and Exchange, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Institute on assimilation of Gov't Pubs in Study of Research, 1979 (Box 4)
    - National Commission on New Technological Uses of Copyrighted Works (CONTU) (Box 4)
      - Report, 1977 (Box 4)
      - General, 1970-1977 (Box 4)
      - (FRASE), 1976-1978 (Box 4)
      - General, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Old People - Sheviak/Ferstl ICH, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Education Resources Information Center (ERIC) materials, 1970-1973; undated (Box 4)
    - Advisory Panel Meeting, June 1970 (Box 4)
    - Evaluation Study of Products and Services, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Journals, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
    - Panel (Box 4)
      - General, 1970 (Box 4)
      - Benson, Mr. Gregory (Educators), 1970 (Box 4)
      - Cutter, Mrs. Virginia (Dissemination), 1970 (Box 4)
      - Gephart, Professor William J., 1970 (Box 4)
      - Glovinsky, Mr. Sanford (Dissemination), 1970 (Box 4)
      - Ingle, Mrs. Gladys (Dissemination), 1970 (Box 4)
      - Kiewitt, Miss Eva (Dissemination), 1970 (Box 4)
      - King, Dr. Charles D. (Dissemination), 1970 (Box 4)
      - Marks, Mrs. Barbara (Dissemination), 1970 (Box 4)
      - Mattas, Mr. Frank (Educators), 1970 (Box 4)
      - McCleary, Mr. William (Dissemination), 1970 (Box 4)
      - Raddick, Mr. Robert (Educators), 1970 (Box 4)
      - Stevens, Mrs. Patricial (Educators), 1970 (Box 4)
      - Way, Mr. S. Russell (Educators), 1970 (Box 4)
    - PROBE, 1973 (Box 4)
    - HEGIS, undated (Box 4)
- Correspondence, 1972-1992 (Box 4)
  - Ahrens, E.H. Onteoro Club, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Bailey, Herbert, Princeton University Press, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Ball, Alice D., U.S. Book Exchange, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Bard, Judy Kay, MLS, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Barksy, James, Commercial Publications, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Batick, Albert, (COSMOS) Correspondence, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Bowen, Carroll, Consultant University Presses, 1972-1975 (Box 4)
  - Braunstein, Yale, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
  - Brown, D.J., Associated Scientific Publishers, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Clark, Harold, Xerox, 1975 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, L516, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, Vice President Pinnell, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, Vice President O'Neil and Fry, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Cummings, Martin M. National Library of Medicine, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Dessauer, John P., 1975 (Box 4)
  - Ewick, Ray, State Library, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Graduate Library (GLS) Reports and Dean Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Letters of Reference, pre-1980 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1980s (Box 4)
  - Purdue Instructional Media Research Unit, 1972-74 (Box 4)
  - Staples, Jim, Qualification Exams, 1992 (Box 4)
  - Title IIB (Institute Correspondence), 1969 (Box 4)
  - University of Colorado Libraries, 1974 (Box 4)
  - White, Herb, Letter, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Williams, Dr. Gordon, Center for Research Libraries, National, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
- Research and Study Proposals, 1966-1982; undated (Box 5)
  - General, 1966-1982; undated (Box 5)
    - Analysis of Photocopying and Feasibility Test of Possible Royalty Payment Mechanism, White/Hasen-Jager/Pratt, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Analysis of Research Proposals, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Armstrong-Kiewitt Proposal OE Self-Instruct Multi-Media Packages, 1974 (Box 5)
    - ASIS Index - Hilmark United Grant Proposal, undated (Box 5)
    - ASIS Paper Changing Patterns in Scholarly and Research Journal Populations - Guide for Mangers by Herbert White and Elizabeth Johnson (GLS), 1977 (Box 5)
    - Becker, Joe, Becker & Hayes, 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - A Community Analysis Model for Monroe County Public Library" by Graduate Library School, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Council on Library Resources Kaser Proposal to Purchase United States Office of Education (USOE) tapes, funded, January 8, 1975 (Box 5)
    - A Database of Research Affecting Military Technical Information Services Final Report by Miles A. Libbey and Bernard M. Fry, Research Center Graduate Library School, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Department of Education/IU Foundation, 1982 (Box 5)
    - Disadvantaged Institute (Box 5)
      - General, 1969; (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Planning Committee, 1968-1970 (Box 5)
    - Distribution, Control, & Utilization of State and Local Government Document Proposal, 1972-1974 (Box 5)
    - Economics and Interaction of the Publisher-Library Relationship in the Production and Use of Scholarly and Research Journals by Bernard M. Fry and Herbert S. White, Graduate Library School, November 1975 (Box 5)
    - EURATOM Thesaurus, 1969-1970 (Box 5)
    - Evaluation Study of the Effectiveness of Fed. Funding of Public Libs. NCLIS/White, Fry, Shuman, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Fry-Welsh Proposal - OE Bib Control & Distribution of Gov't Docs, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Government Document Round Table (GODORT) Proposal, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Government Documents Study Proposals by American Association of State Libraries, 1966-1970 (Box 5)
    - Government Publications, Final Report, A Research Design for a Comprehensive Study of the Use, Bibliographic Control, and Distribution of Government Publications by Fry, Bernard M. et.al., 1970 (Box 5)
    - Government Publications, Correspondence (Box 5)
      - Research Design, 1970 (Box 5)
      - 1970-1972 (Box 5)
    - State Libraries (AASL), 1966-1970 (Box 5)
    - Government Publications, Proposals, Research Center for Library and Information Science (RCLIS), 1971-73 (Box 5)
    - Hernon and Whitbeck, GPR, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Humanities Project, 1976-1981 (Box 5)
    - Illinois Info Retrieval Research Lab, 1961-1992 (Box 5)
    - Independent Learning Program, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Journal Questionnaire (Box 5)
      - General, 1974; (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Problems and ventures, 1974-1975 (Box 5)
    - Journal Study, undated (Box 5)
    - Journal Study, Chicago Periodical Bank, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - Library Manpower Study, Wasserman and Bundy, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
    - Midwest Regional Library Network, Progress Report (MIDLNET) (Box 6)
    - Study, 1975 (Box 6)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) (Box 6)
      - General, 1976 (Box 6)
      - Planning Study, 1976 (Box 6)
      - Final Report, 1977 (Box 6)
      - Proposal Rewrite for Mr. White, 1976 (Box 6)
      - Related Research and Projects, 1976 (Box 6)
    - Oehlerts Proposal, 1974 (Box 6)
    - Overall Methodology, 1980-82 (Box 6)
    - Picatinny - Technical Libraries, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
    - Proposal to AEC, 1969 (Box 6)
    - Proposals (Box 6)
      - Council on Library Resources, 1967 (Box 6)
      - Graduate Library School HGS Title II-B, 1970-1971 (Box 6)
      - Lilly Endowment, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
      - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
      - National Institute of Health, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
      - Research Center for Library and Information Science (RCLIS), Computer Exchange Program, 1969-1972 (Box 6)
      - RCLIS Multi-School R&D for L.I. Networks, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Pratt-Shuman Proposal OE Creation of a Lib Plan Data Base, 1975 (Box 6)
    - Reports, Technical, etc. for background, ca.1970 (Box 6)
    - Research File, 1973-1976 (Box 6)
    - Research and Graduate Development Fellowships, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Research Grant, 1979 (Box 6)
    - RPF Materials Sent to Consortium, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Shepherd, Clayton A. - Proposal, Rockefeller Foundation, undated (Box 6)
    - Utterback, James, 1969 (Box 6)
    - White, Herbert S.The Library Management in the 'Tight Budget 70s', 1976 (Box 6)
  - ERIC [Education Resources Information Center] Research, 1969-1977 (Box 6)
    - General, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Advisory Panel on Dissemination (Box 6)
      - 1970 (Box 6)
      - 1971 (Box 6)
    - Analysis, 1972 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 6)
    - Evaluation Study Proposal, 1971 (Box 6)